Moving on to endocrine pancreas,
recall that the pancreas is sort of two organs in one.
There's an exocrine pancreas that produces the digestive enzymes
that are then secreted into the small bowel.
And then there's the endocrine pancreas,
which is what we're going to discuss in this particular chapter.
The endocrine pancreas is actually composed of clusters of cells
called the islets of Langerhans.
Each islet contains multiple cell types,
and these cell types then produce one particular type of hormone.
For example, insulin is secreted by the beta cells.
Examiners like you to know that the beta cells
lie in the center of the islets.
That's an important thing that shows up on exams.
Recall that insulin is the major anabolic hormone of the body.
It upregulates GLUT4 receptors on skeletal muscle and adipose tissue.
This then allows for glucose to enter into those tissues,
which then lowers the serum glucose.
When glucose enters into those tissues,
it leads to increased glycogen synthesis,
increased protein synthesis,
and increased synthesis of fat or lipogenesis.
Recall that insulin is opposed by glucagon,
which is secreted by the alpha cells of the islets,
and the glucagon increases blood sugar
via breakdown of glycogen or glycogenolysis
and via breakdown of fat or lipolysis.
Here's a picture of an islet,
and I put this picture here to remind you
that the beta cells sit in the center of the islet.
First disorder is type 1 diabetes mellitus.
This is when you have an insulin deficiency,
which then leads to a metabolic disorder
characterized by hyperglycemia.
So again, key problem is that you lose the ability to produce insulin.
This occurs because you have an autoimmune destruction of the beta cells by T lymphocytes.
It's a type 4 hypersensitivity.
The characteristic finding will be inflammation of the islets.
Board examiners like you to know that.
You will see inflammation of the islets.
It's associated with HLA-DR3 and HLA-DR4,
and patients can have autoantibodies against insulin in their blood.
These are often present and may be seen years before the actual clinical disease develops.
Now, this will manifest in childhood.
That's when it usually occurs,
and it manifests with features of insulin deficiency.
So because there is insulin deficiency,
the patients will have high serum glucose.
Of course, a lack of insulin will lead to decreased uptake by skeletal muscle and fat.
In addition, the patients will have weight loss and low muscle mass,
and again, that's because they have unopposed glucagon,
and the glucagon will result in gluconeogenesis,
which requires amino acids, and so you'll break down muscle.
Glycogenolysis, where you'll break down glycogen,
and lipolysis, where you will break down fat.
They can also have polyphagia, which means that they eat a lot.
In addition, the patients will have polyuria with glucose in the urine,
and will also be drinking a lot.
Now, the idea here is that you'll have a high glucose in the blood,
and that will result in a high filtration by the kidney.
The hyperglycemia will exceed the renal ability to resorb sugar,
and you'll start losing sugar in the urine.
That's an osmotically active substance, which will also draw water with it,
and so again, you'll have polyuria with glucose in the urine,
and polydipsia, where the patients will be drinking a lot.
And the treatment is lifelong insulin.
One of the feared complications, and one of the classic mechanisms
by which type 1 diabetes can present, is diabetic ketoacidosis.
This is characterized by excessive ketoacids within the serum,
hence the term diabetic ketoacidosis.
It often arises with stress, for example, infection,
and the idea here is that when you have stress, you get release of epinephrine,
and epinephrine increases glucagon.
Now, glucagon, of course, will increase lipolysis,
and when you increase lipolysis, that's going to result in increased free fatty acids.
Those free fatty acids will go to the liver and be converted to ketone bodies,
and the ketone bodies, for example, are beta-hydroxybutyric acid and acetoacetic acid.
Of course, these acids would then be the hallmark of diabetic ketoacidosis.
Clinically, the patients will have a very high sugar,
and that's because the glucagon is also inducing gluconeogenesis and glycogenolysis,
and so the sugar will be very high.
They'll have an anion-gap metabolic acidosis,
and that is because they've got ketoacids floating around in the blood.
They'll have hyperkalemia, and this can happen for a few different reasons.
Number one, insulin is useful for driving potassium into cells,
and so if they don't have insulin, the potassium will be outside of the cell,
giving them a hyperkalemia.
And number two, when they get an acidosis,
one of the buffering mechanisms is to put hydrogen into the cell and bring potassium out,
and so they'll have a high potassium within their serum.
Now, it's important to note that much of this potassium will actually be lost in the urine,
and so over time, although the potassium is high in the blood,
they're actually depleting the body of potassium,
and so overall, the potassium is low in the body because it's being lost in the urine.
In addition, the patients will have cost-mall respirations,
and that's because they're trying to blow off this acidosis.
They'll have dehydration because the hyperglycemia is leading to a massive diuresis,
and they can have a fruity-smelling breath due to the presence of acetone within their serum.
The treatment involves giving fluids.
The patients are often dehydrated because of the diuretic effect of having so much sugar in the urine.
In addition, insulin is given to counter the effects of glucagon and to replace insulin.
In addition, you'll have to replace electrolytes, in particular potassium.
Recall that although the patients are hyperkalemic, they've lost a lot of potassium in the urine.
When you give insulin, that's going to force potassium into the cells,
and also when you reverse the acidosis, potassium will also go back into the cells,
and so these patients can quickly become hypokalemic,
and so you need to replace potassium while all of this is going on.
Now, in type 2 diabetes, you have end-organ resistance to insulin that leads to hyperglycemia.
This is the most common type of diabetes.
Its incidence is rising.
The classic patient is a middle-aged obese adult.
Obesity leads to a decreased number of insulin receptors on the skeletal muscle and the adipose tissue.
That's very high yield for board examinations.
They like you to know the mechanism of insulin resistance,
and it is due to a decreased number of insulin receptors.
There's a very strong genetic predisposition for type 2 diabetes.
In fact, the genetic predisposition for type 2 diabetes is stronger than it is for type 1 diabetes,
and that's also a high yield board association.
In these particular patients, early on, the insulin levels are increased,
and that's because there's an insulin resistance, and so the pancreas and so the islets will produce excess insulin.
However, later there will be insulin deficiency as you get beta cell exhaustion.
One of the interesting high yield points that you'll see on histology is that the islets will become full of amyloid,
and so you can clearly see that there's all this amyloid within this islet here,
and that's very high yield for the purposes of exams.
Now, clinically, these patients will have polyuria and polydipsia.
At the same time, they'll have hyperglycemia, but often it's clinically silent,
and in fact, many patients with type 2 diabetes don't even know that they have the disease.
The diagnosis is made by detecting a high blood sugar.
You can do so by finding a random blood glucose greater than 200,
by measuring a fasting blood glucose, which should be greater than 126,
or by doing a glucose tolerance test where you give the patients a specific amount of glucose
and then measure the glucose after a few hours,
and the presence of greater than 200 milligrams per deciliter of glucose
two hours after the glucose load is also sufficient to make a diagnosis of diabetes.
Treatment involves weight loss by a diet and exercise,
and in fact, this is the first-line treatment.
You could give drug therapy to counter the insulin resistance,
and finally, in the end stage of the disease, the patients do become insulin-dependent.
One of the key complications in type 2 diabetes
is the risk for hyperosmolar non-ketotic coma.
This is when the patients get very high blood glucose levels,
which then leads to a life-threatening diuresis.
So again, the high glucose will get filtered by the kidney,
and the glucose is an osmotically active agent,
which will then result in a massive diuresis.
Now, this would then result in hypotension and coma,
and in particular, it's important to note that ketones are absent.
In this particular case, the patients do have small amounts of circulating insulin,
and that insulin is sufficient enough to counter the effects of glucagon,
and so ketones are usually absent.
Again, going back to the term here,
hyperosmolar, high blood sugar, non-ketotic, you don't have ketones, coma.
You get life-threatening diuresis, which could put the patient into coma.
Now, the last discussion, as far as diabetes is concerned,
is to cover the complications of diabetes.
And so basically, what I would like to remind you
is that there are two major mechanisms by which you get complications in diabetes.
The first is non-enzymatic glycosylation of vascular basement membrane.
Non-enzymatic means you don't need an enzyme,
and glycosylation means that you're sticking sugar onto something.
And so when you stick sugar onto the vascular basement membrane,
it's going to result in certain complications.
When this occurs on the large and medium-sized vessels,
you're going to increase the risk for atherosclerosis.
And this then leads to many of the complications of diabetes.
For example, cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death,
and cardiovascular disease is caused by atherosclerosis.
Peripheral vascular disease is a leading cause of non-traumatic amputations in diabetic patients.
And so atherosclerosis and all its related complications will occur.
In addition, diabetics also get non-enzymatic glycosylation of their small blood vessels.
That then leads to highline arteriolosclerosis,
and we covered this in detail in the vascular chapter.
Now, the classic location for highline arteriolosclerosis would be in the kidney.
And recall that if this is the afferent arteriole, and this is the glomerulus,
and this is the efferent arteriole, a couple of things can happen.
Number one, you're going to get preferential involvement of the efferent arteriole.
That's going to increase the pressure within the glomerulus,
creating a hyperfiltration injury.
The initial phase will be that you'll get microalbuminuria.
Eventually, you'll get sclerosis of the mesangium, resulting in Kimmel-Steel-Wilson nodules,
which will then result in nephrotic syndrome.
So one complication of the highline arteriolosclerosis within the kidney will be nephrotic syndrome.
Another complication will be that you will get some arteriolosclerosis of the afferent arteriole.
This will then decrease the blood supply to the glomerulus and can result in diffuse sclerosis of the glomerulus,
which would then, of course, also result in chronic renal failure.
And so these patients can develop chronic renal failure over time as well.
Finally, the third complication of non-enzymatic glicosylation is that you will have non-enzymatic glicosylation of hemoglobin.
And when you get non-enzymatic glicosylation of hemoglobin, that produces a special hemoglobin called hemoglobin A1c.
And it's important to note that hemoglobin A1c is a marker of glycemic control,
because remember that the red blood cells, they last 120 days.
And so you can get an idea of how well the sugar has been controlled over a period of time by looking at hemoglobin A1c.
Here's a picture of highline arteriolosclerosis.
Remember that highline arteriolosclerosis refers to the fact that you get pink material within the walls of small blood vessels,
hence the term arteriolo.
And this then decreases the luminal caliber, resulting in the complications that we've already described.
Here's a picture of a kidney with glomerulosclerosis.
The idea here is that you've got a shrunken kidney that appears scarred on its surface.
And the reason it appears scarred on its surface is because you've got all that sclerosis going on in the glomeruli that I've already described.
Again, this would then lead to chronic renal failure that is classically seen in diabetics.
The second complication of having a high sugar is that you'll get asthmatic damage in certain cells.
Now it's important to note that there are some cells in the body that will take up sugar without the need for insulin.
For example, the Schwann cells have the ability to take up sugar without insulin.
And so if you've got a high blood sugar, you're going to get high sugar within the Schwann cells.
When you have high glucose within the Schwann cells, aldose reductase will convert the glucose to sorbitol.
And sorbitol will lead to osmotic damage.
This is very high yield.
Now when you cause osmotic damage of the Schwann cells, recall that the Schwann cells, they myelinate the peripheral nervous system.
And so that's going to result in the neuropathy that's seen in diabetics.
In addition, the pericytes of the retinal blood vessels can take up sugar without insulin.
And so let's remind ourselves that if this is the small blood vessel within the retina,
and you've got the endothelial cells here, we're just talking about the capillaries.
Again, endothelial cells sitting on basement membrane.
Remember that underneath the endothelial cells in the microvasculature, in the capillaries, for example, in the venules,
you've got these small cells called pericytes.
And so here's an example of the pericytes here.
What happens with a high sugar is that sugar goes into these pericytes.
Aldose reductase converts the sugar to sorbitol.
That then causes osmotic damage, and the pericytes die.
When the pericytes die, you will then weaken this blood vessel wall, which will then result in an aneurysm.
And so you can get aneurysms within the retina.
These aneurysms can rupture, and then you get hemorrhage, and that then causes blindness.
And recall that diabetes is an important cause of blindness.
And finally, the lens can take a glucose even without insulin.
And so the high glucose will go into the lens, will be converted to sorbitol by aldose reductase, again, high yield.
And that will then result in cataracts, and so that's also a complication seen in diabetics.
Moving on to pancreatic endocrine tumors, these are tumors of the islet cells.
They're often a component of MEN1.
MEN, again, is multiple endocrine neoplasia, where you get neoplasia of multiple endocrine organs.
In MEN1, the classic finding would be parathyroid hyperplasia, pituitary adenoma, and then a pancreatic endocrine tumor.
Insulinoma is when you have a tumor that produces insulin.
You get episodic hypoglycemia with mental status changes that are relieved by glucose.
So the glucose would be down because of the insulinoma.
The insulin would be up.
And very important, very high yield, the C-peptide would also be up.
Recall that when the body produces insulin, it also produces an additional protein with it called C-peptide.
And so if you have a high insulin with a high C-peptide, it indicates that you're making the insulin within the human body,
and hence you probably have an insulinoma.
However, if the patient has a high insulin with no C-peptide,
it means that they perhaps may be injecting themselves with insulin,
for example, to seek the attention of medical professionals.
Gastrinoma is a tumor that produces gastrin.
Recall that gastrin goes to the parietal cells of the stomach and then causes the parietal cells to produce acid via their proton pumps.
So if you have a gastrinoma, you're going to get excess production of acid by the parietal cells,
which will then result in treatment-resistant peptic ulcers.
That's called Zolliger-Ellison syndrome.
These ulcers can be multiple, and they can extend into the jejunum.
And so these are some of the classic features of a gastrinoma.
A somatostatinoma is when you have a tumor that produces somatostatin.
Somatostatin inhibits gastrin, and so the patients will have low acid production by the stomach, or achlorhydria.
Somatostatin also inhibits cholecystokinin.
Recall that cholecystokinin, or CCK, is important for contraction of the gallbladder,
and so when you have a somatostatinoma, you won't have contraction of the gallbladder.
And lack of contraction of the gallbladder will increase the risk for gallstones and for steatorrhea.
Of course, if you're not putting the bile into the small bowel, you won't be able to digest fat very well,
and so the patients will get steatorrhea.
VIP-oma is a tumor that produces VIP, or vasoactive intestinal peptide.
This will result in a watery diarrhea, achlorhydria.
Remember that VIP inhibits gastric acid secretion, and hypokalemia.
And so these are the key findings in VIP-oma.
And that concludes our section on the endocrine pancreas.